In the year 1901,
في سنة 1901، أخذت امرأة تدعى اوجستا
a woman called Auguste was taken to a medical asylum in Frankfurt.
إلى فرانكفورت من أجل العلاج.
Auguste was delusional
كانت أوجستا مختلة،
and couldn't remember even the most basic details of her life.
ولا تستطيع تذكر تفاصيل حياتها الأساسية.
Her doctor was called Alois.
وكان طبيبها يدعى ألويس.
Alois didn't know how to help Auguste,
لم يعرف ألويس كيف يساعد أوجستا،
but he watched over her until, sadly, she passed away in 1906.
لكنه اعتنى بها إلى أن توفيت للأسف في عام 1906
After she died, Alois performed an autopsy
بعد وفاتها، قام ألويس بتشريح جثتها،
and found strange plaques and tangles in Auguste's brain --
ووجد ترسبات وتجاعيد غريبة في دماغ أوجستا..
the likes of which he'd never seen before.
شيء لم يشاهده من قبل في حياته.
Now here's the even more striking thing.
الصدمة المؤلمة أكثر:
If Auguste had instead been alive today,
هي لو أن أوجستا على قيد الحياة اليوم،
we could offer her no more help than Alois was able to 114 years ago.
لن نستطيع أن نقدم لها مساعدة أكثر مما قدم لها أوليس قبل 114 عاماً.
Alois was Dr. Alois Alzheimer.
ألويس هو الدكتور ألويس الزهايمر.
And Auguste Deter
و أوجستا ديتير
was the first patient to be diagnosed with what we now call Alzheimer's disease.
كانت أول مريضة تشخص بما يطلق عليه الآن مرض الزهايمرز.
Since 1901, medicine has advanced greatly.
منذ عام 1901، تطور الطب بشكل كبير.
We've discovered antibiotics and vaccines to protect us from infections,
لقد اكتشفنا المضادات حيوية واللقاحات لتحمينا من الالتهابات،
many treatments for cancer, antiretrovirals for HIV,
والعديد من الطرق للتعامل مع السرطان و مضادات للأيدز،
statins for heart disease and much more.
ومخفضات الكوليسترول لأمراض القلب وغيرها
But we've made essentially no progress at all in treating Alzheimer's disease.
ولكننا لم نتقدم خطوة واحدة لعلاج مرض الزهايمرز!
I'm part of a team of scientists
أعمل مع فريق من العلماء،
who has been working to find a cure for Alzheimer's for over a decade.
ولانزال نحاول البحث عن علاج للزهايمرز لأكثر من عقد.
So I think about this all the time.
وهذا ما يشغل بالي طوال الوقت.
Alzheimer's now affects 40 million people worldwide.
حاليا يصيب الزهايمرز 40 مليون شخص في العالم.
But by 2050, it will affect 150 million people --
وفي عام 2050، سيصيب 150 مليون شخص،
which, by the way, will include many of you.
و سيكون العديد منكم من ضمنهم بالمناسبة.
If you're hoping to live to be 85 or older,
إذا كنتم تأملون العيش لعمر 85 فما فوق،
your chance of getting Alzheimer's will be almost one in two.
ففرص إصابتكم بالزهايمرز هي واحد من اثنين.
In other words, odds are you'll spend your golden years
بمعنى آخر، غالبا ما ستقضون سنوات تقاعدكم
either suffering from Alzheimer's
إما صراعا مع الزهايمرز،
or helping to look after a friend or loved one with Alzheimer's.
أو رعاية لصديق أو حبيب مصاب بالزهايمرز.
Already in the United States alone,
في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية فقط
Alzheimer's care costs 200 billion dollars every year.
يكلف الزهايمر 200 بليون دولار سنويا.
One out of every five Medicare dollars get spent on Alzheimer's.
واحد من كل خمسة دولارات تنفق على الرعاية تصرف على الزهايمرز.
It is today the most expensive disease,
واليوم هو أكثر الأمراض تكلفة،
and costs are projected to increase fivefold by 2050,
ومتوقع أن تتضاعف تكلفته خمس مرات في 2050
as the baby boomer generation ages.
حينما يكبر جيل الخمسينيات.
It may surprise you that, put simply,
ببساطة قد تصدمكم،
Alzheimer's is one of the biggest medical and social challenges of our generation.
الزهايمرز أحد أكبر التحديات الطبية والاجتماعية لجيلنا،
But we've done relatively little to address it.
ولم نفعل سوى القليل لمواجهته.
Today, of the top 10 causes of death worldwide,
واليوم هو أحد أكثر 10 أسباب للوفاة على مستوى العالم،
Alzheimer's is the only one we cannot prevent, cure or even slow down.
وهو السبب الوحيد الذي لم نتكمن من منعه أو علاجه أو حتى إبطائه.
We understand less about the science of Alzheimer's than other diseases
نعرف عن الزهايمرز أقل مما نعرف عن الأمراض الأخرى
because we've invested less time and money into researching it.
لأننا وضعنا القليل من الوقت والمال لمحاولة فهمه.
The US government spends 10 times more every year
تصرف الحكومة الأمريكية على أبحاث السرطان
on cancer research than on Alzheimer's
عشرة أضعاف ما تصرفه على الزهايمرز سنويا،
despite the fact that Alzheimer's costs us more
على الرغم من أن الزهايمرز يكلفنا أكثر،
and causes a similar number of deaths each year as cancer.
ويسبب نفس عدد الوفيات كالسرطان سنويا.
The lack of resources stems from a more fundamental cause:
انعدام المصادر نابع من سبب جوهري:
a lack of awareness.
وهو انعدام الوعي.
Because here's what few people know but everyone should:
وما يعرفه القليل، وحري بأن يعرفه الكل:
Alzheimer's is a disease, and we can cure it.
أن الزهايمرز مرض و يمكننا علاجه.
For most of the past 114 years,
خلال الـ 114 عاما الماضية،
everyone, including scientists, mistakenly confused Alzheimer's with aging.
أخطا الجميع بما فيهم العلماء باعتبار الزهايمرز هو الشيخوخة.
We thought that becoming senile
و اعتبرنا أن الخرف مرحلة
was a normal and inevitable part of getting old.
طبيعية و لامفر منها من التقدم بالعمر.
But we only have to look at a picture
ولكن كل ما علينا هو النظر لصورة
of a healthy aged brain compared to the brain of an Alzheimer's patient
لدماغ مسن و صحي، و نقارنها بدماغ مصاب بالزهايمرز
to see the real physical damage caused by this disease.
لنرى التلف الفعلي الذي يسببه المرض.
As well as triggering severe loss of memory and mental abilities,
بالإضافة للضعف الحاد في الذاكرة والقدرات العقلية،
the damage to the brain caused by Alzheimer's
فإن تلف الدماغ الذي يسببه الزهايمرز
significantly reduces life expectancy and is always fatal.
يقلل من عمر الإنسان وهو حتما مميت.
Remember Dr. Alzheimer found strange plaques and tangles
أتذكرون الترسبات والتجاعيد الغريبة التي وجدها د.الزهايمر
in Auguste's brain a century ago.
في دماغ اوجستا في القرن الماضي؟
For almost a century, we didn't know much about these.
لقرن من الزمان، لانزال نجهل الكثير عنها.
Today we know they're made from protein molecules.
الآن نعرف أنها مكونة من جزيئات البروتين.
You can imagine a protein molecule
تخيلوا جزيء البروتين
as a piece of paper that normally folds into an elaborate piece of origami.
كورقة اوريجامي تطوى دائما بدقة بالغة.
There are spots on the paper that are sticky.
وهناك نقاط لزجة عليها،
And when it folds correctly, these sticky bits end up on the inside.
وعندما تطوى جيدا فإن النقاط اللزجة تكون للداخل.
But sometimes things go wrong, and some sticky bits are on the outside.
ولكن تحدث أخطاء أحيانا، وتكون النقاط اللزجة للخارج
This causes the protein molecules to stick to each other,
وهذا ما يجعل جزيئات البروتين تلتصق ببعض،
forming clumps that eventually become large plaques and tangles.
وتشكل كتلا تتحول بالتدريج لعقد و ترسبات كبيرة.
That's what we see in the brains of Alzheimer's patients.
وهذا ما نراه في دماغ المصابين بالزهايمرز.
We've spent the past 10 years at the University of Cambridge
لقد قضينا العشر سنوات الماضية في جامعة كامبريدج
trying to understand how this malfunction works.
نحاول فهم كيف يتكون المرض.
There are many steps, and identifying which step to try to block is complex --
هناك مراحل عديدة، ومعرفة أي مرحلة يجب إيقافها ليس بالسهل.
like defusing a bomb.
كأنك تحاول نزع فتيل قنبلة،
Cutting one wire might do nothing.
قطع سلك قد لا يؤثر شيئا،
Cutting others might make the bomb explore.
وقطع آخر قد يفجر القنبلة.
We have to find the right step to block,
لابد أن نعرف المرحلة التي يجب إيقافها،
and then create a drug that does it.
وعندها نصنع عقارا لذلك.
Until recently, we for the most part
ولانزال نعمل و لوقت قريب
have been cutting wires and hoping for the best.
على قطع الأسلاك والحلم بالنتائج.
But now we've got together a diverse group of people --
ولكن لدينا الآن مجموعة متنوعة من العلماء...
medics, biologists, geneticists, chemists, physicists, engineers and mathematicians.
أطباء وأحيائيين وعلماء جينات وكيميائيين وفزيائيين ومهندسين ورياضيين،
And together, we've managed to identify a critical step in the process
ومعاً استطعنا معرفة مرحلة خطيرة في تكوّن المرض،
and are now testing a new class of drugs which would specifically block this step
ونجري الاختبارات على مجموعة أدوية تمكننا من إيقاف هذه المرحلة،
and stop the disease.
وإيقاف المرض كلية.
Now let me show you some of our latest results.
دعوني أريكم اليوم بعض ما توصلنا إليه.
No one outside of our lab has seen these yet.
لم ير أحد خارج مختبراتنا هذا من قبل.
Let's look at some videos of what happened when we tested these new drugs in worms.
دعونا نرى بعض اللقطات لمفعول هذه الأدوية الجديدة على الدود.
So these are healthy worms,
هذه ديدان صحيحة،
and you can see they're moving around normally.
وكما ترون فهي تتلوى طبيعيا،
These worms, on the other hand,
ولكن هذه الديدان هنا،
have protein molecules sticking together inside them --
لديها جزيئات بروتين ملتصقة ببعض،
like humans with Alzheimer's.
كالبشر عندما يصابون بالزهايمرز.
And you can see they're clearly sick.
وكما هو واضح أمامكم فهي مريضة
But if we give our new drugs to these worms at an early stage,
ولكن عندما نعطي دوائنا الجديد لهذه الديدان في مرحلة مبكرة،
then we see that they're healthy, and they live a normal lifespan.
فسنرى أنها معافاة و تعيش فترة حياة طبيعية.
This is just an initial positive result, but research like this
هذه فقط نتيجة إيجابية أولية، إنما بحث كهذا
shows us that Alzheimer's is a disease that we can understand and we can cure.
يرينا أن الزهايمرز علة يمكننا محاولة فهمها و إصلاحها.
After 114 years of waiting,
بعد 114 عام من الانتظار،
there's finally real hope for what can be achieved
لدينا اليوم أمل حقيقي بما يمكن تحقيقه
in the next 10 or 20 years.
خلال العشر أو العشرين سنة القادمة.
But to grow that hope, to finally beat Alzheimer's, we need help.
ولننمي هذا الأمل، لنتغلب على الزهايمرز نحتاج العون.
This isn't about scientists like me --
أنا لا أخاطب العلماء مثلي...
it's about you.
بل أخاطبكم،
We need you to raise awareness that Alzheimer's is a disease
نحتاجكم لزيادة الوعي بأن الزهايمرز مرض،
and that if we try, we can beat it.
وأننا لو حاولنا فسنغلبه.
In the case of other diseases,
خذوا مثالا لأمراض أخرى،
patients and their families have led the charge for more research
قاد المرضى و عائلاتهم مسيرة المطالبة بالمزيد من الأبحاث،
and put pressure on governments, the pharmaceutical industry,
وضغطوا على الحكومات و شركات الأدوية
scientists and regulators.
و العلماء و صناع القرار.
That was essential for advancing treatment for HIV in the late 1980s.
وهذا مادفع بعلاج الإيدز للتحسن في نهاية الثمانينيات.
Today, we see that same drive to beat cancer.
وفي الوقت الحالي، نرى نفس المطالبات لعلاج السرطان.
But Alzheimer's patients are often unable to speak up for themselves.
ولكن مرضى الزهايمرز في الغالب لا يستطيعون المطالبة،
And their families, the hidden victims, caring for their loved ones night and day,
وعائلاتهم، الضحايا الخفية للمرض، مشغولة برعايتهم ليلا و نهارا
are often too worn out to go out and advocate for change.
ومنهكة للخروج والمطالبة بالتغيير،
So, it really is down to you.
ففعلا ليس لدينا سواك.
Alzheimer's isn't, for the most part, a genetic disease.
إن الزهايمرز مرض لا ينتقل بالوارثة في معظم الحالات،
Everyone with a brain is at risk.
كل شخص لديه دماغ معرض للإصابة.
Today, there are 40 million patients like Auguste,
واليوم هناك 400 مليون مصاب كأوجستا،
who can't create the change they need for themselves.
وليس بوسعهم صنع أي تغيير هم بحاجته.
Help speak up for them,
ساعدوا بالتحدث عنهم،
and help demand a cure.
وساعدوا بطلب العلاج.
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)